<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarkeable considerations upon the life, and services of Monsieur Villeroy. Together with certaine politicall observations upon the fall of Seianus. Translated out of the originals by Sr. T.H.</title>
            <title>Remarques d'estat et d'histoire, sur la vie et les services de monsieur de Villeroy. English</title>
            <author>Matthieu, Pierre, 1563-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07272</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847706</idno>
  <idno type="VID">12763</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240932421</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 17668</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S112452</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99847706e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1074:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarkeable considerations upon the life, and services of Monsieur Villeroy. Together with certaine politicall observations upon the fall of Seianus. Translated out of the originals by Sr. T.H.</title>
                  <title>Remarques d'estat et d'histoire, sur la vie et les services de monsieur de Villeroy. English</title>
                  <author>Matthieu, Pierre, 1563-1621.</author>
                  <author>T. H. (Thomas Hawkins), Sir, d. 1640.</author>
                  <author>Manzini, Giovanni Battista, 1599-1664. Della peripetia di fortuna. English. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 79, [1]; [2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. G[riffin] for Godfrey Emerson, and are to bee sold at his shop, in Little Brittaine neere Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: P. Mathieu.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Remarques d'estat et d'histoire, sur la vie et les services de monsieur de Villeroy.</note>
                  <note>Sir T.H. = Sir Thomas Hawkins.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes a reissue, with title page cancelled, of "Politicall observations upon the fall of Sejanus" by Giovanni Baptista Manzini, London, 1634 (STC 17293.5). It is a translation, also by Hawkins, of: Della peripetia di fortuna.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Sejanus, Lucius Aelius, d. 31.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Villeroi, Nicolas de Neufville, --  Seigneur de, 1542-1617.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:1"/>
            <p>Remarkeable CONSIDERATIONS upon the Life, and Services Of <hi>MOVNSIEVR VILLEROY.</hi> Together with Certaine Politicall Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations upon the fall of <hi>SEIANVS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Translated out of the Originals by S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>T. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E.G.</hi> for <hi>Godfrey Emerson,</hi> and are to bee sold at his shop, in Little <hi>Brittaine</hi> neere Aldersgate, 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:2"/>
            <head>To the King.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold here the ruines of an excellent Fabrique, whence goodly, and rare pieces may be taken to beautifie new buildings. They are the wise observations of the most an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of your Counsellors of state, during his six &amp; fifty years service in the greatest state-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of your Crowne. They who account it no lesse glory to imitate merit, then to succeed to honours, wil make use of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as of a Torch enkindled
<pb facs="tcp:12763:3"/>by Truth, the eldest daughter of light. If they follow him, and the blast of passion, or Interest make them not dissolve, or slip aside, your Maiesties good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions may be seconded with happy counsels, and your desires with great and glorious effects.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. Mathieu.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notices">
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:3"/>
            <head>Advertisements.</head>
            <div type="testimonial">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E who affords not honour to Mounsieur Villeroy,</hi> denyeth it to vertue: I was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at the last was done him at Lyons in the Church of the Minims, and there heard his learned discourse, whom <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Great</hi> so much had lov'd and esteemed, who had beene for aboue foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen yeares the Chrysostome of the Court, and of whom Fraunce may more truly say, then Greece of Pericles, that the Temple of Perswasion was seated on his lips.</p>
               <p>And although hee forgat nothing, which appertained to the merit, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this occasion, yet cannot I thinke
<pb facs="tcp:12763:4"/>though he well acquitted himselfe, that I stand disobliged from what I owe to the memory of this man.</p>
               <p>He reaped all that was exquisite, and excellent in this subject, I but gleane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, yet it is sufficient I let it appeare, that as to model the pourtrait of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury at Athens, they tooke the picture of Alcibiades, so perfectly to delineate a states-man, we must make use of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="nihil_obstat">
               <p>Nihil obstat quò minùs typis mandetur, &amp; cum utilitate legatur praesens Tractatus Petri Mathaei, &amp;c. </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>3 Ianuarij. 1636.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>R. Weckherlin</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12763:4"/>
            <head>HISTORICALL OBSERVATIONS Upon The Life and Services of <hi>MOVNSIEVR VILLEROY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW lively, and strong soever the apprehension of a noble spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit be, it hath need of helpe, and direction, and the greatest men seeke the assistance of those who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded, in that profession they intend to pursue: It is to stand upon the highest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of admiration, to imitate no man, and to be imitated by all. <hi>Satrius Rufus</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Cicero, Cicero</hi> found flowers of Greeke
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12763:5"/>Eloquence in the actions of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> who boasted to imitate <hi>Pericles; Pericles</hi> tooke <hi>Pisistratus</hi> for a paterne: and I verily thinke there is not any States-man will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to walke in the manage of affaires on the tracts of <hi>Villeroy,</hi> and derive profit from his experience.</p>
            <p>The name of a States-man hath so large an extent, and participateth qualities so emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and excellent, that it meeteth with few subjects worthy of it. It onely belongs to him, who hath never blemished his reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by any act of disloyalty: hath perfect knowledge of Men, of Affaires, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, is knowing in all sorts of occurrences, yet thinkes not others ignorant, He presumes not to know all, he goeth not alwayes the same way, nor turnes out of a good one; he shewes nothing in his opinions, which reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth of the impudence of flattery, or the basenesse of servitude; Hee suffers not his owne interest to out-run the publique; Hee never resolves on any thing out of passion, through mood, choler, or hastinesse, (foure dangerous rockes of prompt and subtile wits.) Finally, there is order in his discourse,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12763:5"/>judgement in his writings, sincerity in his opinions, constancie &amp; silence in commands, diligence and facility in resolutions.</p>
            <p>ROYAL <hi>Science,</hi> which is called Reason of State, or politique Prudence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth in a vigorous strength of wit, and an absolute experience in the manage of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affaires; the knowledge of which is so hard, that life is too short to understand it. Science comprehendeth those things which tend to demonstration and constancie; Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is practised in changes, and revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the one walkes in the high way of Law and Reason, the other divides it selfe, and departs from the ordinary course.</p>
            <p>For which cause <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> a little before his death (for ever to bee lamented) sayd, that he then began to understand what rule was, nor had he learned it but from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, which he tearmed his great Booke, wherein <hi>Noman long reades, who becomes not knowing.</hi> So that as it is impossible to finde a Common-wealth, such as <hi>Plato</hi> designed, or an Orator as <hi>Cicero</hi> representeth, or a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine according to <hi>Xenophon,</hi> so it is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12763:6"/>to have a States-man accommodated with all things requisite to counsell a great Prince, or to assist to the Governement of a powerfull Republique.</p>
            <p>FRANCE which was never barren in the production of men of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, hath not seene any man who sooner began this profession, nor hath longer exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised it, then <hi>Mounsieur Villeroy,</hi> and if in the last Act of Life, the desire of Eternity had permitted him to thinke of the world, I make no doubt but he tasted this comfort, that hee left none behind him, who had served the King, and State longer, with more trust, or in greater occasions, then He. <hi>Who is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired by all, cannot in his profession be compared with any.</hi> A man must rise very high to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine parts so transcendent.</p>
            <p>He hath served five Kings, toyled six and fifty yeares, lived threescore and fourteene, saw the end of forraigne broyles, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of civill. Hopes and Favours to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, Rise and Fall: <hi>The Court-monster, which hath two hearts, and two tongues,</hi> and is so fruitfull in change, so constant in incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12763:6"/>furnished him with examples, which he was able to apply to all sorts of events.</p>
            <p>HE came not alone to the Court, nor inconsiderately, to make up a fortune in that place: The wealth his grandfather left him: and the consideration of the services done by him to King <hi>Francis</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> and to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Queene Regent in his absence, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready raised him above a vulgar esteeme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the liberality of his father, and his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage at eighteene yeares of age to the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Aube-spine,</hi> secretary of the Commands, and the most trusty of the Queene-mothers servants, gave him assurance, that nothing but time opposed his fortune.</p>
            <p>It is a matter very difficult to raise it at Court, how industrious so ever one be, if a powerfull favour, or some notable service lay not the foundations of it. How many brave spirits wither away for that they have not this sunne in their East? They are gemmes, which lose much of their value and lustre by not being handsomely set.</p>
            <p>HE likewise derived another maine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12763:7"/>from his entring into affaires in this his first youth. <hi>It is every hard to thrive at Court in the Evening:</hi> What a deale of time to unclew so many webs? what watchings to arrive at repose? what affronts to meet with honour? what calumnies to get out of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie? There are things harsh and uneasie, which patience and custome makes fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, and supportable, and especially a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine annihilation of ones owne will. <hi>Who thinkes to preserve his owne will entire, shall never make great progression in Court.</hi> It is a prison, at the entrance into which, armes must be layd downe, liberty, contentment, repose, and nothing retained but hope and patience. For which cause <hi>Mounsieur Villeroy</hi> so often sayd, <hi>That a man must never despaire at Court, and patience and importunity over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>QVEENE <hi>Katherine,</hi> who had so much judgment to make choyce of wits, such liberality to oblige them, employed him in affaires, sent him into Spaine, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of certaine Articles of peace made in the yeare 1559, and to Rome to Pope <hi>Pius</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12763:7"/>the fourth, concerning the difference of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedencie, which had never been before dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted against the most Christian Crowne. It grieves me, that setting downe this, I am more than a hundred leagues distant from the originall of a letter written with his own hand, upon the occasion of his embassage; had I meanes to relate some passages thereof, it should appeare his understanding went on from the first, in a way quite other than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary capacities.</p>
            <p>The prime peece in the equipage of a States-man, is, a good and solid judgement. Good wits with little labour, small time, and much dexteritie, attaine their desire: Other, who are dull and heavie, are like barren land, which the more it is cultivated, is the lesse fruitfull, or as ignorant Mariners, who still complaine of the sea or the windes, &amp; strike not into the haven, but by accident. A Spirit free and prompt, understands himselfe in Counsels, in Dispatches and Affaires; and as he conceiveth matters in a different manner from others, so his words are not vulgar, they still come to the poynt, and by wayes which least appeare. He is subtile in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12763:8"/>quicke in replies, and easily apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: His resolutions are perspicuous, and cleare, He is not confused in discourse, hath grace in things fayned, gravity in matters of truth: He knowes how to propose an affaire, to divide it, to pursue, and end it.</p>
            <p>IN the beginning he had an eye very open to doe nothing countrary to good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As reputation beginneth, it growes or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clineth. Above all, integrity is to bee wished, for all vertues are to little use, if that be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; It is the bottome of that vessell, which breaking, all that is powred in, runnes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough. <hi>The words of an honest man counterpoise an oath;</hi> He speakes to men, as if he spake to God; He cals things by their owne names, openly favoureth good men, sweetly adviseth such as erre, hath not an care, for calumnies, slaunders, nor flatteryes, and if <hi>dissimulation (the new court virtue,)</hi> be to be used, he doth it so soberly, that neither innocency, nor verity hath cause to complaine. He desires not to make appeare all, what he can, to the hurt of any man.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:12763:8"/>
            <p> AT his returne out of <hi>Italy,</hi> the Queene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother procured him the reversion of <hi>Aube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spine,</hi> his Father in lawes charge, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his fidelitie and vigilancie to King <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, who called him his <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> trusted him with his most inward thoughts, dictated to him a booke of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and certaine Poems; and among the rest, that, which hee addressed to <hi>Ronsard,</hi> wherein he sayth,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ronsard,</hi> thy wit more sprightly is than mine,</l>
                  <l>My body younger, abler much than thine.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ronsards</hi> answer began in this manner.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Such as I am you <hi>(Charles)</hi> shall be one day,</l>
               <l>Life hopelesse of returne, still flies away.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But as nothing is wanting where the grace of God aboundeth, I am of opinion that not any thing so much furthered his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, as the firme, and constant zeale he maintained in Catholique Religion, in times, when the greatest knowing men went out of the way, and novellisme (which hath so powerfull charmes over the French) had corrupted many brave wits both in Schooles
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12763:9"/>and Parliaments. For after the conference of <hi>Poissy,</hi> the Edict of <hi>Ianuary</hi> having ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Temple,</hi> and permitted <hi>Altar,</hi> against <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar;</hi> and when the principall Cities of the Kingdome weresurprized, there was such a tottering, that I have heard him say to <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> and to some elder than himselfe, that the Queene-mother to accommodate her selfe to the times, and to comply with the strongest, seemed not to be an enemy of this novellisme, and permitted testimonies of her affection to it in her Cabinet. <hi>Necessitie is a violent, and rough Counsellor in affaires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This young man continuing stable in the way of Antiquitie, and abhorring this change, wherein ancient Discipline, and the Hierarchy, was scoffed at by those, who believed the way they pursued was the most assured for safetie, and the shortest to make a fortune, having powerfull protections in Court: but this constancie augmented the first affection which King <hi>Charles</hi> bare him. The good liking of Kings is acquired, or manured by such, as apply themselves to the first inclinations of their youth, or to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises &amp; humours of their pleasures, or to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12763:9"/>encrease of their revenewes, or to the extent of their conquests. All other wayes are not sure enough, and when one is arrived thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the best is, that, of <hi>Loyaltie,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT the age of 24. He alone executed the charge of <hi>Secretary of State,</hi> &amp; that of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> being vacant, it was united to it. It was not at that time in such splendor, and consideration, as it is now. I have elsewhere made it appeare, that under <hi>Lewis</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, there was no <hi>Secretary of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> as also that the first man in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber received the command of expedition, which was resolved and decreed between the King and the principall Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell; in such sort, that many great actions were seene to be both subscribed, and signed by sundry Secretaries. But ever there was with the Prince some trusty man, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke the care of the most secret resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the dispatch of the most impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Such was <hi>Balue</hi> under <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11<seg rend="sup">th</seg>, <hi>Brisonnet</hi> under <hi>Charles</hi> the 8<seg rend="sup">th</seg>, the Cardinall of <hi>Amboise,</hi> &amp; <hi>Robertet</hi> under <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg>.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12763:10"/>
            <p> THE Chauncellor <hi>Hospitall,</hi> and <hi>Morvilliers,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Orleans,</hi> Keeper of the Seale, and <hi>Aube spine,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Limou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin,</hi> three great men of this Age, who had the chiefe care of the Kings affaires, impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their experiences to him, and enabled him, <hi>To admire little, and to know much.</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds are weighed against Diamonds, and wits are refined by wits in affaires, which presse forward, and transport the most hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, and stupid natures, as Torrents carry along, &amp; unloose the weightiest stones. And as to become eloquent, the imitation of the most exact Pieces of auncient <hi>Orators</hi> should be proposed: so, to prepare a brave Spirit for <hi>State-affaires,</hi> the shortest way, is, the example of those, who have long practised them. <hi>More, men profit by example, and labour, than by precepts and discourse.</hi> But as great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions doe not perpetually happen to exercise the understanding, nor great capacities are still found to handle great affaires; It is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite happines for such as have easie accesse, and familiar conversation with those able men, who being raised upon the highest Spheares of government, see, before other
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12763:10"/>the storme, and calme, at distance, judge of events, and know the source and sequele of affaires: for as one is parched in the Sunne, and perfumed in odours, without much adoe, so such frame their judgement upon all sorts of resolutions.</p>
            <p>HE began his endevours upon great workes; at which time his Spirit, not poorely groveling upon inferiour things, raysed it selfe by strength of wing to the highest, as to its Center. <hi>It is fit a States-man know the qualitie of his owne spirit, and extent of it.</hi> There are some, who the more they are advanced, the lesse appeare; and other, who will not admit so much light as to make themselves to be well seene: for charges and businesse discover men. <hi>Some would bee thought worthy of a place, if they had it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The comparison of the diversitie of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to that of statues, is not amisse. The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> employed two excellent Sculptors, (<hi>Phidias</hi> and <hi>Alcmenes</hi>) to make the head of <hi>Minerva,</hi> and beholding them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after they were finished, they scoffed at that which <hi>Phidias</hi> pourtrayed, it being but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12763:11"/>roughly designed, and admired the other; which with unspeakeable cunning, layd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all the most delicate &amp; gentle touches.</p>
            <p>But when they were raysed upon two high Columnes, that, of <hi>Phidias,</hi> lessening by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance to its due proportion, appeared to be exactly wrought, and <hi>Alcmenes</hi> his Piece, without forme, the height so taking away the beauty, that it seemed no other than a Bowle ill rounded.</p>
            <p>There likewise are Spirits, which appeare according as they are more or lesse exalted; some having not vigour enough, unlesse they be perpetually in the supremest region of affaires, other goe not so high, and their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility mounteth but to a certaine degree, past which they are not knowne, and much adoe they have to know themselves. <hi>The head turnes, and the eyes dazle in high places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were no slight affaires handled by the Kings Councell in those times, all dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches were most important, and all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels tended to battailes, and victories. I have heard him say, that he was present at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Edict of Pacification, in the first troubles in the yeare 1563. The difference of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12763:11"/>religion, which had divided the <hi>French</hi> in Gods service, divided them likewise in their service to the King.</p>
            <p>Hereupon were two great factions raised, of which religion was the pretext, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment the cause. The Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> held all the world in Sentinell. The passage of the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of feare to the one, and of courage to the other. After Queene-mother had yeelded up the power of Regencie to the King, shee let him see the Provinces of his Kingdome. The enterview of this Prince with the Queen of <hi>Spaine</hi> at <hi>Bayon,</hi> and the secret counsels held between Queene-mother, and the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> occasioned great designes. The King being at <hi>Meaux,</hi> saw the forces of the Prince of <hi>Condè</hi> so neare, that he was advised to steale to <hi>Paris</hi> by night, under the conduct of the <hi>Switzers.</hi> There was a conference at Saint <hi>Denis</hi> betweene the Kings Deputies, the Chauncellor <hi>Hospitall,</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans, Limousin,</hi> Saint <hi>Sulpitius,</hi> with <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> where <hi>Villeroy</hi> also was. It was wayted on by the battaile, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Constable</hi> dyed; <hi>Mounsieur</hi> the Duke of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12763:12"/>
               <hi>Anjou</hi> was declared chiefe, and <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the Army, <hi>Aube-spine</hi> dyed the next day, and <hi>Villeroy</hi> alone entred into charge, and the times furnished him with more businesse, than was left him.</p>
            <p>CHARLES the ninth sent him to the Emperour <hi>Maximilian,</hi> upon the treaty of his mariage with the Princesse <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</hi> This third voyage much holpe to dispose and fortifie his judgement; so fit it is that such as desire to bee employed in great affaires, should see forraigne Countreyes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially neighbours, which may become e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. But if the curiositie of seeing, be not accompanied with the affection of judging, and remembring what is seene, all the profit is lost, and vapours away in meere vanitie.</p>
            <p>It is not enough to admire rarities abroad, or to bee delighted with things pleasing, it importeth to consider, how they are gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in peace, and warre, how the Prince is served, in what his forces consist, what hee wanteth, how his fortresses are built, how provided with munition, and defended, how he entertaines his men of Armes, which way
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12763:12"/>he may be assayled, or surprized; <hi>Whether he have more wood to heat his Oven, than Corne to send to the Mill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Young men easily observe the vices of nations, and sow the seeds of quarrels, when they upbrayd such with them who passio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately strive to maintain the honour of those nations, and who believe their owne is still exempted from ordinary vices.</p>
            <p>Ignorance of affaires both forraigne and domestique, is no lesse shamefull in a States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, than in a Physitian, who nothing feares the temperature of mans body. An igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance which many times leades Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into lost designes, with such blindnesse, that they often make warre against those, of whom they should aske peace.</p>
            <p>THE King foreseeing the course of of his owne life would not bee long, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him to his brother, when hee was going into <hi>Poland.</hi> He died at <hi>Bois S. Vincent,</hi> and the affection he bare him, reduced him into his memory at that time, when hee had none at all for worldly matters. If this Prince made use of violent counsels, <hi>Villeroy</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12763:13"/>gave them not, for he many times told him, that the Prince who had more care to make himselfe to bee feared than beloved, was sure in the end to bee more hated than feared. <hi>Feare is an ill Schoole of dutie.</hi> This cruell, and abhominable word (Let them hate, so they feare) is not Christian like; the very <hi>Romans</hi> knew it not but in the time of <hi>Sylla.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VILLEROYS service was presently so necessary, that after the death of his first Master, hee was no lesse favoured by the second. Discovering the black clowd, which brake into a prodige of revolt and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, he gave the King this just counsell, to reunite the Royall stock in one and the same beliefe, and designe, and not to divide <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> that they might not acknowledge any other Prince for head but the lawfull.</p>
            <p>Hee employed him, to get two men to come into the Court, who were most deare unto him, the Duke of <hi>Allencon,</hi> and the King of <hi>Navarre. Ambition, which more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidereth the scope of desire, than dutie,</hi> had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him the affection of the one, and novell opinions, contrary to ancient beliefe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12763:13"/>had debaushed the conscience of the other. He sent Queen-mother to them, and would have her to be assisted by <hi>Villeroy</hi> in this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation. <hi>It is a great happinesse for a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, when hee is employed to make an accord betweene the children of the family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HE was the first who had notice of the purpose of creating a <hi>new order of Knighthood.</hi> Perhaps he might have done beter to have restored, that, of S. <hi>Michael</hi> into grace, as the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> hath been praysed, to have raysed, that, of the <hi>Golden Fleece.</hi> This Prince having other thoughts, instituted that, of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and believed <hi>Villeroy,</hi> who told him, that communicating it to few, it thereby should bee the more illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>A Prince ought to bee very retentive in conferring titles of honour, which are the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of merit.</hi> There was no reason to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Themistocles</hi> the Crowne, who vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the <hi>Persians</hi> in the battell of <hi>Salamina,</hi> and give it to <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> who fled out of the field.</p>
            <p>IT is well knowne, how passions
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12763:14"/>swayed, and overflowed against this Prince, and how many writings insolently free, were published against him; he caused the authors to be punished, but it was contrary to <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy's</hi> advice, who had learned from the wise, that <hi>Paper suffers all,</hi> and that, <hi>the more Satyrs and Pasquils are forbidden, the more they are sought after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not the duty of a States-man to wound the minde of his Prince with all manner of bruites, nor to inflame his anger against those, who invent or spread them to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of his reputation. There is no kinde of offence ought more to bee dissembled, than that of <hi>Tongues, Pennes,</hi> and <hi>Impressions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Generous soules account themselves sufficiently revenged by letting it appeare they can be revenged. <hi>Alexander</hi> mocked at them, <hi>Augustus</hi> recompensed them, <hi>Tiberius</hi> dissembled them, <hi>Titus</hi> scorned them. <hi>It onely is for great Kings to doe well, and heare evill.</hi> Three good Emperours, <hi>Theodosius, Arcadius,</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> father and sonnes, have on this left so divine a law, that it seemeth to have beene dictated by heaven. See it in <hi>French,</hi> as it is in <hi>Latine,</hi> in the seventh <hi>Title</hi> of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12763:14"/>ninth <hi>Code. If any one through want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie, and excesse of impudence, believes hee is permitted to invade our reputation, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligne and insolent slanders, and (drunke) with passion, becomes a detractor of our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, we will that hee for it bee not lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any punishment, nor suffer any thing rough or rigorous: For if it proceed from le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie, hee is to bee pardoned; if from fury, he is to bee pittied. If from injury, it is to bee forgiven: and therefore wee will, that the entire knowledge thereof bee preserved, to the end, that considering the qualitie of words by the persons, wee may advise whether wee should pursue or dissemble them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>COMPLACENCE is so familiar with Princes, that one had need to have a soule very religious, not to love better to please with <hi>Truth,</hi> than to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by flattery. <hi>There is nothing in Kings Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces so rare as simple truth.</hi> An Archbishop of <hi>France</hi> sayd one day to Queen-mother, during the assembly of the generall States of <hi>Paris, That it was now fiftie yeares that truth had not gone through the doore of her Cabinet</hi> And an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12763:15"/>Bishop preaching in the <hi>Louure</hi> last yeare, sayd to the King, <hi>That it entred not into Kings houses, but by stealth, and through the windowes.</hi> The Prince is much bound to a faithfull servant, who tells it him with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and discretion, and to be well served it is fit he ordaine honours, and rewards tyed to the <hi>Truths</hi> told him, in doubtfull and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant cases, the concealing whereof would be prejudiciall.</p>
            <p>Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> loved a certaine Lord of her owne Nation, <hi>Villeroy</hi> perceiving the Princes, and prime men of the Kingdome did complaine of it, and that such complaints are ever the seeds of partialities, had the boldnesse to beseech her to moderate this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which she did; and he whom she af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, used such modesty &amp; good discretion therein, <hi>That his fortune was never subject to ill adventures, which alwayes meet with those, who abuse favour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Henry</hi> the third after his returne out of <hi>Poland,</hi> was quickly weary of military ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, suffering this his warlike humour to dissolve in the delights and vanities, which peace bringeth. Hee instituted divers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12763:15"/>of saeculars, who lived, not alwayes, but for certaine houres, regularly. His prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall retreat was at <hi>Bois S. Vincent,</hi> whither he drew the Nobility: and for that affaires followed him every where, hee would that, <hi>Villeroy</hi> who had the care of those, which could hardly bee put over to the next day, should take the habit as other, and should have a peculiar place, as it were a parlour, to receive packets, and heare Courriers. But perceiving expeditions were retarded, hee sayd to him as truly, as generously, <hi>(Sir) Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and obligations are considered according to time, and that is the cause why old debts should be payd before new: you have beene King of France before you were head of this Companie, your conscience obligeth you to render to regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, what you owe it, before you grant to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, what you have promised it. You may dispense with your selfe in the one, not in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: you weare not Sackcloth, but when you list, but you have the Crowne on your head perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually: and no lesse weighty is it in this retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than in affaires. This is to speake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Prince cannot give too much time to pietie, <hi>but hee must sometime leave God for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12763:16"/>God,</hi> who permits himselfe to bee found in affaires, and contents himselfe with a good intention. Let heaven bee of brasse for <hi>France;</hi> while pietie lives in the heart of its Kings, it shall need no other raine; no more than Egypt, which cares not since it hath the water of <hi>Nilus</hi> that fattens and refresh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it.</p>
            <p>But they ought to desire it may be most pure, without art or inforcement, walking with head erected, without laying it on this or that side. It avoy deth these two extreames, <hi>Impietie</hi> and <hi>Superstition.</hi> Many Princes by the one have braved God, and have thought ill of him by the other. <hi>Impietie</hi> blindeth the soule, <hi>Superstition</hi> maketh it dull-sighted. <hi>Piety loves God, impiety contemnes him, as if he were a man: Superstition feares him as if he were not a God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SEEING this Prince loved soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and made his ordinary abode at <hi>Paris,</hi> he gave him counsell to send some principall Lords of his Councell throughout the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, that his Majestie might there be seene by the effects of his justice, since they were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12763:16"/>deprived of the contentment of his presence, imitating the Sun, who stirring not out of heaven, sendeth his rayes thoroughout the world. If they be good men, and of quality, they every where advance the service of the Prince, their words are so many flaming arrowes, which with their heat melt the Ice contracted in distant places.</p>
            <p>A Prince cannot better preserve the good will of his people, than by employing men, who onely affect a generall good. Of all the precepts which the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> left to his ion <hi>Philip</hi> the second, this is observed to be the best. <hi>That not being able to be in so many remote and distant places, he should handle the matter so, as daily he might bee seene by his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and justice, disposing them in the hands of persons of great innocencie and vertue, that his subjects might not have occasion to bee sory for his absence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE King who to bee revenged, purposed tragically to end the Assembly of the States of <hi>Blois,</hi> sent him a Ticket of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, for no other reason but for feare, lest he and <hi>Belieure</hi> might divert him from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12763:17"/>and lest much depending on the Queene-mothers dispose, they might give her some notice of it. For greatly hee feared the spirit of this mother, who had a great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer over his, besides, he saw not clearly into her practises. <hi>The Spirit of Man is very hard to be knowne, but that of a woman never.</hi> Hee thought the bloud of these two Princes would quench the fire they had enkindled; but he more redoubled the flame. For a while after, there was almost a generall revolt. The <hi>Saturniall feasts</hi> were renewed, wherein servants became Masters, and Gally-slaves no sooner loft the Oare at the signall given by the Captaine, but that the most obliged fell off from their duty. He then offered the King the continuation of his service, which his principall servants forsooke; but hee, not understanding the weaknesse of his own Counsels, imagined, hee might slip over a man so necessarie, and confident.</p>
            <p>A Prince diggeth out his owne eyes, when hee inconsiderately riddes himselfe of a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, who knoweth his affaires. Almost all <hi>Poland</hi> had conceived an implacable hatred against <hi>Gavaric</hi> the Kings most faithfull
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12763:17"/>Counsellor, <hi>Lescus,</hi> and <hi>Blanc</hi> threatning him to choose another King, if he banished him not. <hi>Garvaric</hi> was content, and besought the King to throw him into the sea, since he was the cause of the Tempest, protesting that hee not onely would willingly lose his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, but his life also for the safety of his Prince, and the Peace of his Countrey. <hi>Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> declared, <hi>he had rather retire, and live as a private person, than stay in a kingdome under so unjust, and unreasonable a condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VILLEROY then, hoping neither for safety, nor protection, that way, cast himselfe on the side wherein his Father, his Sonne, his Wife, his Family, and his goods were. He much desired to expect in one of his houses till those stormes might fall, but being unable to abide there, but at the discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the violence of the times, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to forsake the way of lustice for the way of Prudence. <hi>In intestine broyles, the worst side is to be of none: In particular quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels it is a poynt of wisedome to stand neuter.</hi> Who onely respecteth the place, goeth off when he will; who is of a faction is not so
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12763:18"/>admitted, that he can leave it, without rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithstanding hee was in such account with both, that although discretion and equity appeared not in these confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but by the light of <hi>Harguebusses,</hi> all, which belonged to him was regarded, his family felt not the miseries of the siege of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> his friends caused him to keepe victuals secretly, and sometimes in drummes, his house at <hi>Conflans</hi> was preserved by a Lord who honoured the Father, and had beene bred with the Sonne. At the taking of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toise,</hi> a great man of this kingdome had the care to cause all the moveables of his house of <hi>Halincourt</hi> to bee brought into a strong Citie of his government, and when the peace was concluded, hee sent them backe to him in Carts, as it were by Inventary, there being not perceived the losse of any the least par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. It was an admirable providence of God to see, that against all likelihood, it should be restored him, and that his charge of <hi>Secretary of State,</hi> should likewise be rendred him.</p>
            <p>How rigorous usage soever hee received from his king, his affection towards his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12763:18"/>was no whit exasperated. <hi>Henry the Great</hi> told me one day the strange resolution this Prince had had against the Duke of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencon</hi> his brother, and commanded me not to forget it in his history, saying: <hi>It was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to observe the faults of Princes, to the end that such as come after them may not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in that way, wherein they lost themselves.</hi> I framed a discourse upon it, and shewed it to <hi>Mounsieur Villeroy,</hi> to submit it to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He assured me he had never heard of it. The King hearing this answere, sayd: <hi>You ought to beleeve me, because I speake the truth, and you cannot but prayse</hi> Mounsieur Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy, <hi>who would not speake it to prejudice the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his master.</hi> To this may bee referred his answere made to <hi>Tinteville,</hi> saying unto him, that none but be was able to write the history of that time, <hi>I am</hi> (sayth he) <hi>too much bound to the memory of</hi> Henry <hi>the third to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the dreadfull, and tragicall death of this Prince, and on the next day after, hee sent to one of the most trusty servants of his successor, an expresse messenger, who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented unto him, that the harshnesse of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12763:19"/>warre would be the destruction of the state, and dissembled not with the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> that it would ruine Religion, and advance their faction, who went about to reforme it.</p>
            <p>This desire of peace rendred him odious to such as sought to profit by warre; the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards decryed his good intentions; bad <hi>French</hi> called him the <hi>Politician,</hi> &amp; although the Cities in this desperate liberty felt many miseries by warre, and created many more by their partialities, yet the name of <hi>Peace</hi> was so odious amongst them, that quiet spirits were accounted turbulent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators.</p>
            <p>It was through the constancie of his judgement, and of one other of much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and great understanding, that the Duke <hi>de Mayne</hi> found it to be the best, and most ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturous counsell which was ever given to a Prince, to cause foure of sixteene to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, who through a furious act of injustice, had dishonoured this royall Parliament. By the like advice he drave away a petty tyrant from the <hi>Bastile,</hi> which hee had made the store-house of his thests, and lastly, gave the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12763:19"/>government to a noble spirit, whose constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and unshaken fidelity <hi>Henry the Great</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded, for he esteemed an honest man, on what side soever he were.</p>
            <p>AS it is not hard to guide a ship which sayles before the winde, so it is not difficult to give counsell where there is neither maine impediment, nor perill; but rough stormes try good Pilots, &amp; great affaires strong judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Such appeared, that, of <hi>Villeroy</hi> in this over-whelming tempest, where it was dangerous both to give counsell, and to refuse.</p>
            <p>Hee freely told the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> that there was but one of these three wayes to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the kingdome, either to accord with the King, or to reunite all the Catholiques un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head against him; or to submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the protection of the Spaniard. The third being perillous, as contrarie to the lawes of the kingdome, and the humours of the French: and the second very difficult (the Princes of the bloud being straightly united for the interest of their houses) hee advised the first under this condition, that the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12763:20"/>King should re-enter into the Catholique Church, and that hee who had the keyes of it, would open the doore. That his Majestie should be sought unto therein by a notable &amp; celebrious embassage; and publiquely, to justifie their Armes in case hee would not hearken to this just meanes of peace. The times have made it appeare, how many mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have beene avoyded by following this counsell. Those rivers of bloud drawne from all the veines of the Body of <hi>France,</hi> would have served to ciment together great Bulwarkes, to defend it against its enemies. It were to write a history to represent what was done in that time, it sufficeth to tell you that the fruit of his negotiation was the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of <hi>Surenne,</hi> which advanced the Kings conversion, after the truce, which was waited on by peace, as by the daughter on the mother. The people having tasted the sweetnesse of repose, would have no more troubles, the faction of the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> found it selfe weake, and succour failing, every one provided for himselfe.</p>
            <p>AFTER the conversion of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12763:20"/>King, he entred into the Kings service, and as <hi>Aeneas</hi> going from the sack of <hi>Troy,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried along with him his Father, his Sonne, and an important place, which served for the reduction of the rest. The wisest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the obstinate, which shut up their eyes against this growing light, and required more ceremony to returne to their duty, than they had used in their separation.</p>
            <p>The King gave him his charge of <hi>Principal Secretary of State,</hi> &amp; from the very day he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into it, he perceived, order returned to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, to the great comfort of his heart. Hee spared not to say, <hi>I have dispatched more bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse to day with Mounsieur Villeroy, than I did with other in six moneths.</hi> He never spake to him upon any occasion, how strange or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected soever it were, that he delivered not his opinion, grounded either upon reason, or example. He wondred that such a head knew so much, without acquiring in youth ought which is learned by study, or which is gained by bookes; most certaine it is, that had this so vigorous and sprightly a judgement been cultivated by Art and Science, he would have arrived to much more perfection, and say
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12763:21"/>what we can, Theory walkes more solidly than practise, and <hi>bookes shew in a little time, what experience teacheth not, but with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of many yeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HE never negotiated with any man, that he was not too hard for him. There have beene forraigne Embassadors, who were held in their owne countrey to bee Intelligencies and spirits in the discovery and discussion of affaires, who talking with him, found their subtilties were but like beards or eares of corne, encountring with the solidity of such a judgement: their discourse but capritches, their skill but formalities.</p>
            <p>They who mannage affaires, doe all of them propose one same marke, but they goe to it by different wayes, and some sooner than other. The <hi>Italians</hi> by profound discourse penetrate farre into the future: The Spaniards derive their best resolutions from passed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples: the <hi>French</hi> stick upon the present: but <hi>Prudence</hi> regardeth all three time, and ever grounds its reasons upon the necessitie of the present, the profit or losse of the passed, and the foresight of the future. They who were
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12763:21"/>but his halfe friends, affirme his parts were not ordinary; a great integritie free from ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, a great modesty, an exquisite ingenuitie, an incredible vigilancie, opposite to profusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, innovation and disorder. He read all was presented to him, hee put not businesses over to the next day, Hee cleared the Table every day, and dayes and nights are not more equal under the Equinoctiall, than were his words and actions. He carried in the most embroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led confusions, the same countenance which hee shewed in the greatest contentments of the Court. Bruit affrighted not him, who bent not his apprehension, but to just and apparant feares. <hi>To feare all, is cowardice; to feare nothing is stupiditie;</hi> with the same hand with which he presented the evill, hee gave the remedy. The King considering this his goodnesse and dexteritie, often sayd, <hi>I must needs say, Mounsieur Villeroy is a good and gracious servant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He gave audience without trouble, confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, or in patience: the gravitie which one met with in the beginning, was sweetned by a great affabilitie, a matter necessarie for a States-man; for the stoutest spirits are payd,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12763:22"/>and satisfied with good words, which never excoriate the tongue, and are repulsed by harshnesse; They who are sowre, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stere, who heare not with attention, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, nor answer but in anger, destroy the Princes service, who is bound, either in his owne person to heare, and see, or by his ministers, who are his eyes, and eares. <hi>Doe you thinke</hi> (sayd <hi>Rodolphus,</hi> founder of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous house of <hi>Austria</hi>) <hi>that I am chosen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to be perpetually shut up in a Box?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HE used great advisednesse, not to precipitate his counsels; <hi>Henry the Great</hi> proposed a very urgent businesse to him, and seeing his coldnesse, asked him why he spake not: Because (sayth hee) I thought it was a matter of command, not of speech. He desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have his advice in an occasion which concerned a Prince of the bloud, hee answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when Kings deliberate upon any thing, which toucheth their allyes, they must onely consult with nature. <hi>A States-man ought to know upon what, and how hee must give, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to give counsell.</hi> In some matters it is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardice to be silent, in other it is temeritie to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12763:22"/>speake, but in no hand is it permitted to give counsell, before it bee asked. Hee gave the King that good counsell, which greatly ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to establish peace, and destroy the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts of warre, causing <hi>Mounsieur</hi> the Prince, who was at <hi>S. Iohn d'Angely,</hi> to come to the Court, and to bee bred in Catholique religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it might plainly appeare in the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full succession, for this uncertainty occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned feare in mindes, and entertained partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the provinces.</p>
            <p>KINGS are alwayes Kings; but in civill divisions, as they are not acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by one side, so they are not well o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed by the other. This Prince during the warre, had beene often constrayned to play the <hi>Carabin,</hi> to overcome in his Cabinet by sweetnesse, before he fought in the field by valour; Here, to bee a fellow in armes, and there a Soldier. The actions of his Majestie were obscured, as the statue of <hi>Minerva</hi> was veyled during the solemnity of <hi>Plyntheries;</hi> or, as all stood sad at <hi>Rome</hi> whilst the <hi>Salii</hi> (those mad Priests of <hi>Mars</hi>) bare the <hi>Ancylia</hi> through the streetes.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12763:23"/>
            <p> The King well perceived the prejudice which ensued thereon: for as great severitie exasperateth affections, so too much facility vilifieth authoritie. <hi>Villeroy</hi> told him, that a Prince who was not jealous of respects due to Majestie, permitted both the offence, &amp; the contempt: That Kings his predecessors in the greatest confusions, had alwayes carried themselves like Kings: That it was time he should speake, write, and command like a King: That it was not alwaies done, there had before been too much regard of words, too much advisednesse in dispatches, too much consideration in commands. Hee had often entreated those hee should command, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced those who deserved punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and appeased such as had angred him.</p>
            <p>When he was peacefull, they who had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in indifferencie, had much a doe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to distinctions, and order. Insolent presumption, and proud arrogancie (the ordinarie Symptomes or indocible, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant spirits) could not arraunge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves under the lawes of modesty, and duty.</p>
            <p>From that time the King became a King in good earnest, he put the most refractory un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12763:23"/>discipline, and many found themselves under those they sought to precede. Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, which so freely had suffered it selfe to be approched unto, and to be importuned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came so tender, that how little soever it was touched, it shewed it selfe to bee wounded. For which cause the King sayd, <hi>Villeroy</hi> had taught him to play the King, and had she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed him more in six moneths, than hee had knowne thereof in six yeares. He some time after being asked, if hee would keepe the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stivall of the three Kings in the beginning of the yeare, he remembred himselfe what <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy</hi> had sayd unto him, and added; we have but too much played the Kings. <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> King of <hi>Asia,</hi> for having contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Majesty, and not knowing how to bee a King, was surnamed the <hi>Mad-man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee could not learne this lesson from a better master; for precepts to make a King, are not acquired but from rule, and many must be observed to know what the Offices thereof are. Those of private persons are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practised, royall grow not, nor appeare not, but in great occasions.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Adaldague</hi> having beene <hi>Secretarie of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12763:24"/>State</hi> fiftie yeares to three <hi>Othoes,</hi> Emperours, and <hi>Gaspar Schlick</hi> to <hi>Sigismond, Albertus,</hi> and <hi>Fredericke</hi> the third, were reputed skilfull of all the obligations of Emperours: so <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy,</hi> who had already seene the court under the reigne of <hi>Francis</hi> the second, and had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into imployments under the reigne of <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, and had mannaged the most important affaires under <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and was not ignorant of any of the greatest under <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, could alone give this instruction.</p>
            <p>Who teacheth what is to bee done, cannot be ignorant how it is to bee done, which is the cause there is no great difference between those who rule, and such as shew how to rule. They have but one marke to aime at, which is the safetie of the state, both the one and the other are ordained to serve the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; and for this it is, why a <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sayd, that to reigne was to serve, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing this servitude in three words, <hi>To serve the Senate,</hi> by submitting to Counsels; <hi>To serve all,</hi> by looking after the common good; <hi>To serve particulars,</hi> by yeelding right to all, and defending them from injurie.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:12763:24"/>
            <p> SO that hee who can well serve the Prince, can well serve the State, who can play the States-man can play the Prince. It is one samething to appoint or counsel, that, which must be appointed. <hi>All, which serves to rule well, serves to counsell him well who ruleth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In treaties with strangers he hath ever she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the generositie of his spirit. Did hee not say to the Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> who made the first overture of the peace between the two Kings, pursued, and concluded so gloriously by the Chauncellors, <hi>Belieure,</hi> and <hi>Sillcry,</hi> that <hi>Spaine</hi> could not hope for it, without restitution, and <hi>to speake to Princes of restitution, is it not to encrease variance?</hi> what got <hi>Roncas</hi> from him, when hee proposed the Duke of <hi>Savoy's</hi> desire to come into <hi>France,</hi> but that hee should not bee welcome, if he had an intention to with-hold, what hee ought to restore. After the treaty of <hi>Paris,</hi> he sayd: Wee still expect when this Prince will bee delivered of a good word. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Embassadours saying, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> would passe into <hi>Italy</hi> to defend the inheritance of his Nephewes, hee replyed, <hi>That is it we desire: for if wee must breake, the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12763:25"/>cause is just, and the agreement will be the better made, and the more perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This prayse-worthy passion of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this Crowne, made him one of the most unwilling for the exchange of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisisate of <hi>Saluces</hi> for <hi>la Bresse,</hi> hee not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during to counsell the King to lessen his fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier. He considered that <hi>Henry</hi> the third had often repented him to have rendred the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Pignarol, Savilliana,</hi> and <hi>Perouse</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> which were the keyes of <hi>Daulphine,</hi> and <hi>Piemont,</hi> and that the Duke of <hi>Nevers,</hi> not seeming to consent to an act so contrary to the greatnesse of this crowne, had demanded to bee discharged from the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Provinces</hi> beyond the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. This brave Prince, then, foresaw, and foretold, that so soone as this gate were shut up against the <hi>French,</hi> that, of the <hi>Grisons</hi> would not long continue open.</p>
            <p>When a Prince hath any thing from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other by the right of Armes, or other title, how slightly soever it be coloured, hee is not well counselled, to render it againe. It is a Maxime among all Princes, and there is none so tender of conscience, who will mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12763:25"/>wound his owne state, to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date his neighbour.</p>
            <p>A Prince, potent, warlike, and peaceable, thinkes on nothing but the enlargement of his frontiers, and sees no limits of it, but at the poynt of his sword. It is sayd <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh made this answere to those who spake of the weaknesse of the frontiers of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardie</hi> against the <hi>English: Trouble not your selves, my frontier is much further.</hi> As much as to say, that to keepe the <hi>English</hi> in peace, hee would make warre upon them in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he shewed the constancie of his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to strangers, so he made the like gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rositie to appeare in reducing the Kings sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to their duty. Hee hath shewed the greatest of this kingdome, that their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse onely rested in humbling themselves to the Kings will. That there was no safety for them, but in their loyaltie: That the quality of Prime-prince dispensed not with them from being the prime servant to the King.</p>
            <p>When the King undertooke the voyage of <hi>Sedan,</hi> the Lord of that place more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the Kings goodnesse, and the consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his services, than in the defence
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12763:26"/>of his fortresse, desired to speake with <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Villeroy,</hi> who went to finde him out at <hi>Torcy.</hi> The King during their conference, uttered these words, I have sent him a rough Grey-hound. He flattered him not, when he sayd, his unhappinesse and ruine were in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance; his safetie, and hope in humility and obedience. Hee yeelded up the Fort, and it was a notable peece of judgement in <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur Villeroy.</hi> For particular interest made it selfe generall in the passion of those who sayd, they apprehended no other perill for this Lord, but that he had enemies neare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King, who would counsell him to make the Altars of <hi>Rome</hi> to smoke with his bloud in hatred of his religion.</p>
            <p>AT all times <hi>Villeroy</hi> preferred the Kings service before all other thoughts, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting his owne affaires for those of the state, and hence ensued that infinite proofe of his integritie, in that hee very little augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the estate, which his ancestors left him.</p>
            <p>His long services, his incessant industry, the affection of five Kings, might have fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his house with so great riches, as to make
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12763:26"/>them comparable to the wealth of that <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Citizen, who saw rivers to rise and glide along in his owne lands. His father was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Pontoyse, Meulan,</hi> and <hi>Mantes: Henry</hi> the third had given to his sonne the Lieutenancie in the government of <hi>Lyons. Henry the Great</hi> gave it him after the death of <hi>Mounsieur la Guiche</hi> (the flowre of noble, free, and generous soules) he afterward had the government in chiefe, which <hi>Mounsieur de Vendosme</hi> held. And all this compared to the toyls of such a servant, shews, that in the houses of Kings, gratitude is not alwayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to great services.</p>
            <p>Whereupon <hi>Henry the Great</hi> sayd, <hi>Princes have serevants of all prices and fashions. Some doe their owne businesse before their masters: Some doe their masters, and forget not their own; but</hi> Villeroy <hi>thought his masters was his, and used the same eagernesse which another would have done in solliciting his owne cause, or labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his owne vineyard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is neither greatnesse, nor encrease of a state to be hoped for, where it is governed by men more carefull of their owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, than the publique. So likewise it is fit
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12763:27"/>the Prince doe his affaires, who serveth him, that he may have his spirit free, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, he having that (monster <hi>Poverty</hi>) in his minde. <hi>Philip</hi> the second King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> sayd to <hi>Ruy Gomes,</hi> his faithfull servant, <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch my affaires, and I will dispatch thine.</hi> When after his death many spake of the great riches he left, he said, <hi>I thought I had done much better for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never was any man more earnest for the honour of a state, than <hi>Villeroy.</hi> The chiefe poynt of his instructions to Embassadours, who went to serve the King out of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, was, <hi>religiously to preserve the honour of majestie,</hi> to speake nothing imprudently, nor wickedly give eare to any thing against it; and he alwayes made the King in his dispat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to speak as a Prince, great, and awfull, in elegant termes, but such as were most proper for Kings. In his particular letters there was ever something gentile, and which shewed him to bee a man well borne, and long bred in the Cabinet of Kings.</p>
            <p>HOW great soever his credit was, hee abused not the good opinion of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12763:27"/>nor tyred him with troublesome suits. So likewise when hee spake for any one, his recommendation alone was an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted proofe of merit. As hee was not of a humour to doe good to many, so hee would not hurt any, nor oppose the Princes liberalitie to divert it: <hi>To doe no good to any, is Avarice; to hinder another therein, is Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MANY brave spirits would have beene unknowne, if hee had not made them to bee knowne, and ackcowledged. Hee raysed some of them to the Principall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Church, and amongst many, I will make choyce but of two for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, because they were of the same pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, and arrived unto it by two severall wayes, the one by the merit of learning, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therby judgement in affaires.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villeroy,</hi> who was advertised of all, and recommending the first to <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> told him, his great learning had beene so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired at <hi>Rome</hi> in the first voyage hee made after, that, of the Duke of <hi>Nevers,</hi> that would he have stayed, the Pope gave him hope of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12763:28"/>great fortunes, and honour. Hee needed to say no more, to resolve the King, who had notice of this truth in his owne conversion, and in the conference of <hi>Fountainebleau</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other was in such esteeme at <hi>Rome,</hi> that had it not beene for his opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning originall sinne, hee had beene chosen Pope. Hee told his friends hee was bound to <hi>Villeroy</hi> for the <hi>Cardinals-cap,</hi> who not so much considered his merit, as his owne desire to doe the King good service, to the end that such as should have the like intention, might bee assured of the same re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Three great ornaments of <hi>France,</hi> who have had the Scales of the Kingdome (the <hi>Seales,</hi> the sacred marke of the <hi>Kings Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi>) have not concealed that <hi>Villeroy's</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation had holpen their merit.</p>
            <p>HE commended not this vehement passion of searching into, or correcting things past. Hee held his peace in the beginning of the pursuit against <hi>Financiers;</hi> but after the first heat was cooled, he dextrously tooke his time to over-throw it, and told the King, hee had ever observed more trouble than fruit in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12763:28"/>such enquiries, which being too generall, oftentimes involved the innocent with the guilty, and disturbed the peace of Families. This was not, that hee desired not to see abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses corrected, and Sponges squeezed; but there are remedies which make the malady worse.</p>
            <p>Hee desired the people should have meanes to breathe, and our Kings to bee so rich, and potent, that all extraordinary wayes to get money, might bee abolished. Our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volts and seditions have multiplied the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series within, and drawne on fury abroad; <hi>have caused warres, which cannot bee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken without money, nor ended but by peace; and peace not being to bee had but by Armes, Armes are not maintained but by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and money cannot bee got but by tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In these great extremities our Kings have beene constrayned to have recourse to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent remedies, to mow the meadow as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they list. Charges are augmented, and redoubled by the increase of evils, in such sort, that <hi>Philip,</hi> furnamed the <hi>Long,</hi> saw himselfe reduced into so violent, and pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12763:29"/>necessities, that to come out of them, hee demanded the fifth part of the revenew, and labours of his subjects, without any imagination of the times, or distinction of persons.</p>
            <p>The true opinion of his integritie, had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired so great a reputation, that not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his words were weighed, but great heed also was taken of his silence.</p>
            <p>They who flatter Princes, and hold their vices to bee imperfect vertues, approved by their discourse, a designe, which <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerov</hi> dissuaded by his silence. This Prince comming to himselfe, sayd, that <hi>Villeroy</hi> saying nothing, spake much to him. Behold what <hi>power the sole countenance of an bonest man bath!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HE never did any important thing but by his advice, from whom hee derived the knowledge, both of what hee should doe, as also what might happen, when it were done. How often hath hee been heard to say, <hi>Villeroy sayd it; all is done as Villeroy foresaw it.</hi> Newes was brought to him, that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> had caused <hi>Poncas</hi> to bee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12763:29"/>arrested. <hi>Sir</hi> (sayd <hi>Villeroy</hi>) <hi>D'albigny will receive the counter blow.</hi> The prediction was true, and deciphered the strength of a great judgement.</p>
            <p>He so clearly looked into the future, that it is above fifteene yeares agoe since hee sayd that the greatest would one day account it an honour to be present at the raysing of a man, who is ruined for that hee had not a friend to whisper him in his eare, what <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricles</hi> daily sayd to himselfe, <hi>Take heed</hi> Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>thou commandest free men, thou hast to doe with Athenians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A true friend had spoken that to him, which <hi>Villeroy</hi> sayd to a Prince: That hee had observed oftentimes at Court, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes which come leasurely, are the latest ruined. But false amities entertaine men onely with fables, and blasts of winde, which fill empty imaginations. Strong and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous soules suffer not themselves to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by vanity. They are Lyons, which for a time endure to bee led whither one will, whilst their eyes are covered; but when they have liberty to understand themselves, they become untractable. The same Lyons suffer
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12763:30"/>themselves to bee dressed up with flowres to enter into the Games; but if their shadow, or the water shew them that this dresse is not consonant to their generositie, they teare it in pieces. It is onely fit for dull and stupid oxen, who are led along to sacrifices.</p>
            <p>HIS Cabinet hath beene as an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versall map: there was to be seen the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot of the greatest enterprizes of Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, there was scarcely a Monarchy or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique in the world which had not some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to doe there. It was the Academie where the Princes of the bloud, and other Peeres became capable of those things, the ignorance whereof is not excusable. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course was made thither as to a certaine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gister to determine disputes of rankes, to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor the ceremonies of the most solemne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Majestie.</p>
            <p>No man entred into it, who went not out more knowing; men of action there learnt maximes of state, Embassadours there tooke their instructions, Generals of Armies there received direction of designes, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Provinces their power.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12763:30"/>
            <p> So well his counsels served to the preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and continuance of peace, that it is to be feared, lest we have occasion to say, as Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth did, That the peace of <hi>Italy</hi> died with <hi>Galeas</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan.</hi> In this Cabinet <hi>Henry the Great</hi> hath renewed his alliances with his neighbours, hath quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the civill warre of <hi>Italy,</hi> hath establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed the repose of the <hi>Hollander,</hi> hath succou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his allies in <hi>Germany,</hi> hath weighed so many sundry propositions for the glory of this Crowne, and revenge of injuries.</p>
            <p>In this Cabinet it was, where the holy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, everlastingly happy, was proposed, which affoorded <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> sonnes to bee the assured pillars of this Crowne, the love and ornament of strangers. Heaven had ordained, that our <hi>Hercules,</hi> after so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny labours, should repose in the chaste bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some of Princesse <hi>Mary,</hi> daughter of <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> the great Duke of <hi>Tuscany,</hi> and <hi>Ioane</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> daughter of the Emperour <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand,</hi> honoured with two the most supreme titles, which may adorne a generous soule, being wife to <hi>H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nry the great,</hi> and <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>Lewis the just.</hi> It onely belonged to her, that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12763:31"/>her head already crowned with immortall Laurels of vertue, should bee so likewise with the prime crowne of the world; but God, who at the same time had delivered her from a great malady, hath reserved her to bee the eldest Queene of Christendome.</p>
            <p>VILLEROY was one of the three, whom <hi>Henry the great</hi> recommended with so much affection to this great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, and who contrary to all discourse, and humane appearance, have maintained order in affaires, and quiet in the kingdome during her regencie. Whilst shee authorized their Counsell, and cherished their good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Tranquillity, Plenty</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> three markes of the felicity of Empires, <hi>made this kingdom to flourish Constantine the great,</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring that <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> had so happily reigned, comming to the Empire young, and an alien (for he was a <hi>Syrian</hi>) it was answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, that <hi>Mammea</hi> his mother was dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and counselled by personages of great experience, and integritie, <hi>Vlpianus, Iulius Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Fabius, Sabinus, Pomponius.</hi> It was upon the assistance of men of this qualitie, and on
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12763:31"/>the wisedome of such, that <hi>Plotina,</hi> wife of <hi>Trajan,</hi> entring into the Imperiall palace, and turning her selfe towards the people, sayd, <hi>Such as I come in hither, such I desire to come forth.</hi> A head cut off in the <hi>Greve</hi> stupified, and astonished a sedition, and setled the auth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the regencie, which was but newly begun, and <hi>Villeroy</hi> judged this example to be necessarie, although alliance obliged him rather to look after the abolishment, than the punishment of the crime.</p>
            <p>She had in the beginning so much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his counsels, that shee thought they made up a part of the prosperity of her <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie,</hi> as <hi>Athens</hi> termed <hi>Aristides</hi> the felicity of <hi>Greece.</hi> Had they been followed, the first stirres raised against the government, had been stifled in their birth, and the second had not passed 11 rivers, if her conference with <hi>Mounfieur</hi> the Prince, had not beene broken off.</p>
            <p>Shee witnessed her great and just affection, when she visited him in a sharpe sicknesse, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that in her devotions, after shee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred the soule of her husband, &amp; the life of her son, she praied for the health of <hi>Villeroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:12763:32"/>
            <p> THEY who have their tastes so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, that they forsake sweet for sowre, gust full for unsavory, and who in discourse seeke for nothing but Satyricall stings, will say, that the lively colours of so many rare, and eminent qualities, as are in this Table, were to be heightned by the shadowes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches, fastned on the originall. But all this being but dust which marres it not, I remit them to two Apologies, which give a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of all hath beene raysed against his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            <p>It is true; men the most perfect, having imperfections; in him there hath beene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served some excesse of gravitie. Hee knew the great supereminencie which experience gave him over others, and was very carefull to preserve it, when he treated with the most able of all sorts; very sensible, and curious he was upon all passages, which proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>against his judgement, be delighted to see his opinions applauded, and would not hazard them, unlesse hee were sure they should finde credit, or successe.</p>
            <p>I hereupon remember, that when Queene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother sent him in the yeare 1612. to <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12763:32"/>the Prince, and to <hi>Mounsieur Conty</hi> to conjure them to returne to the Court, they sayd of him, that <hi>hee of all men in the world, was able alone to give a great Prince, bold, free, and good counsell; but hee was so accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to goe before, that hee made him to come after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee who sits highest in the Theater, is loth to descend lower for the last commers. It is a harsh thing for such as have growne old in a Princes service, to yeeld to others. They still have in their mindes, that, which <hi>Ctesiphon</hi> sayd to <hi>Eschines. You playd the game, and I layd out the money: you wrote, and I spake: you were the wrastler, and I the spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator: you daunced, and I piped: you dispatched your owne businesse in the government, and I, those of the publique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The treaties of mariage between the King, and Queene, made him odious to such as consider the Crowne of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as a Comet on their side. Then was the time, when good intentions were decryed by some, sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by other, and that Calumny began to assaile them. As <hi>Hercules,</hi> although the sonne of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> was not put into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12763:33"/>of the gods, untill hee had fought with <hi>Hydra:</hi> so he had not arrived to the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of beeing the Oracle of this state, unlesse hee had grappled with this monster. But as <hi>Hercules</hi> made so little account of slaunders, that hee ordained a sacrifice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee would not bee adored but by inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, hee mocked at it, and told his friends, <hi>These kinde of divels are not driven away, but by contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A packet was brought him, surprized at <hi>Orleans,</hi> which was going to the Assembly at <hi>Thoneins,</hi> full stuffed with complaints and reproches against his honour, blaming him for advising these mariages, and urging the execution of them.</p>
            <p>Hee shewed it to all the world, although it was in his power to have made it vapour away, unseene by any: a lesson for others, not to suppresse either a dispatch, or an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, how prejudiciall soever it may bee to their honour, or to the fortune of their friends; for it is fit the Prince be informed of all, and that his service take away all respects and particular interests.</p>
            <p>It was read in the Cabinet, and every one
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12763:33"/>admired the constancie of his soule, which neither shooke nor was stirred with so rough assaults, even before the faces of King, Queene, and Princes, and other ministers of state. <hi>It is weaknesse of spirit, or a confusion of crime, to resent an injurie, which one knowes can neither touch, nor wound us.</hi> A lye cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all.</p>
            <p>FORTVNE, which tryed the constancie of <hi>Scervola</hi> by fire: of <hi>Fabricius</hi> by povertie: of <hi>Rutilius</hi> by banishment, proved the courage of <hi>Villeroy</hi> by meanes which should uphold him, and his enemies shot arrowes against him, which they ought to have kept to defend him. As hee was very odious to some, for having advised the alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Spaine,</hi> so hee was blamed by others, for seeking to delay the accomplishment, and not approving the exchange of the governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Picardie</hi> for that of <hi>Normandy,</hi> hee in a moment saw favour eclipsed.</p>
            <p>Hee retired into his house of <hi>Conflans,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing to himselfe to end in the haven, the yeares he had spent in the floud and ebbe. He had wished this retreat, but seldome enters
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12763:34"/>this wish into the thoughts of Courtiers, who the elder they waxe in it, grow the more in love with it: For they know, when these starres fall from their Spheare, they not onely lose influence, and motion, but light also.</p>
            <p>Hee was not suffered to taste the pleasures of solitude, hee was made to know his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence prejudiced affaires, and that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Assembly of the States held then at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> was scandalized, that a man was taken from the sonne, who had so well served the father.</p>
            <p>Honest men sayd, the safetie of the vessell was doubtfull, since good Pilots were not secure: what assurance is there in such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions? And who wil entermeddle in a state, where <hi>Aristides</hi> is wronged, <hi>Socrates</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and <hi>Aristotle</hi> feares to abide?</p>
            <p>HE returned at the Queenes first command, protesting hee would never bee the cause of hindering the Kings service, and that the resentment of an injury, tooke not from him the sence of dutie. Hee sayd, <hi>The servant was not well advised, who retired
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12763:34"/>upon his Masters anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee returned then, but brought not backe with him, that first reputation, and stayed long, untill his patience had gnawne upon that, which his courage was to devour, being sometimes preceded by those, who hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would have thought it an honour to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: but it being very hard to forgoe men so necessarie, the Queene sent him to <hi>Creil,</hi> and to <hi>Clermont,</hi> when the second mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions began to stirre, and thence to <hi>Guyen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IT is not fit to let a great understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, borne for action, to rest; and old age exacteth a thing unjust, when it makes him retire from attendance on the Prince, but if hee bee not permitted to repose at threescore and thirteeene, nor is dispensed with to goe a voyage of two hundred leagues through the most scorching heates, among feares of sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes, and designes of enemies, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from it, through extreme and insuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table colds, I know not at what age one should sacrifice to repose.</p>
            <p>Having the last yeare made the voyage of <hi>Poictou</hi> and <hi>Brittaigne,</hi> his great yeares, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12763:35"/>indispositions ought to have excused him; but the occasion was too fayre, the journey too honorable, the service too necessarie, to free a man from it, who sayd the servant should not aske whither he was sent, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himselfe with the honour of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and to obey; for he cannot bee ill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated, if his master bee well ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>These long journeyes have difficulties, from which the greatest, who finde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation every where, free not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and those which are but sport and pleasure to the young, are insupportable to the aged.</p>
            <p>For this it was, why <hi>Budaeus,</hi> whom <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the first made one of his <hi>Secretaries,</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to follow him, and assist him to drive away ignorance and barbarisme, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Court-life, a life irksome, insolent, and embroyled. I have often revolved in my minde in those his journeyes, that excellent and learned Latine Letter hee wrot to his sonne, to excuse him with his friends for not publishing a volumne of his Letters. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here the summe of it. <hi>I cannot intend it,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12763:35"/>not so much for the hinderance of affaires, as for the sundry disturbances of Court, and the strange enforcement of often changing place. How many times thinke you, for these fifteene dayes, have I had opportunitie to sit, either to write, or read, in base, streight lodgings, and where one sees not at all, especially when all the rabble comes about one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I doe nothing but runne up and downe. It is more than a mile from the place where the King lyes, to my lodging, if it may bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a lodging, to bee in the same Chamber pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell among Peasants, their poultrey, and all things fed in the base Court, neare unto my hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and unto Cockes distinguishing the night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am besides, constrained to goe to the first Table I finde, and needes must I, (as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, and as Court chances are unexpected) play the smell-feast. The Victualling houses be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not still prepared, nor fit for honest men, wee are enforced to retire into Cottages, where the raine comes in on every side, and where there is no houshold stuffe, but such as the Cyrenians had.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Budeus,</hi> one of the rarest men of his time, who brought <hi>Athens</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> and who
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12763:36"/>was master of the <hi>Requests;</hi> in a time when there was but eight, suffered all this, a man must be very nice to complaine of the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his attendance at Court.</p>
            <p>THE first overtures to end the warre being made at <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> by his dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie, hee was employed to <hi>Poictiers,</hi> to make the truce; hee went from <hi>Tours</hi> to <hi>Loudun</hi> to treat of the peace there. A nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, the most rugged, and difficult which was ever brought upon the Carpet, both for the diversitie of interests, and the multitude of interessed.</p>
            <p>A Marshall of <hi>France</hi> preceded him in this Embassage, two Lords of the Councell as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted him.</p>
            <p>All his Discourses were lessons, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries to enlighten the most doubtfull occurrencies. The prayse-worthy curiosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of one hath observed, and written what hee sayd in conferences both publique, and familiar, and the collection hee made, containeth matters so rare, and singular, that not to mention it, would wrong the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storie.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:12763:36"/>
            <p> Returning from <hi>Loudun</hi> to <hi>Tours,</hi> to shew unto the Queene, the thornes which choked the treatie, hee forbare not to tell her, the Princes complayned, that the King had no better notice of affaires; and spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to his Majestie, hee sayd, it was time hee should take the care of them, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre <hi>the most important before the least serious,</hi> adding, that when Kings neglect their own affaires, there are still some found, who disturbe them, by undertaking to doe them.</p>
            <p>This was a sparke, which falling into his Royall soule, enkindled a resolution in him to bee, that, for which God had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. <hi>It is impossible for a Prince to doe all, and shamefull for him to doe nothing.</hi> The high Chamberlaine of the <hi>Persian</hi> King, drawing a side the Curtaine sayd, <hi>Rise (Sir) and give order in those affairs, which God hath committed to you.</hi> The History judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously observeth the morning: for it is not to be watchfull in affaires to come to them in the evening.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vigilancie</hi> and <hi>Royalty</hi> are borne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It is the eye on the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Scepter.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:12763:37"/>
            <p> Is it possible an eye can sleepe on the toppe of a Truncheon, or on the poynt of a launce? Princes and Ministers of state (as starres) must watch for those that sleepe, and to make themselves capable of their affaires, they must often speake of them, and to more than one, that they engage not the safetie of many to the judgement of one man, as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Severus</hi> consulted with Captains in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes; with Iudges in matter of punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and rewards; with learned men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning examples to bee followed, or es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed; and with Priests in affaires of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>WERE the contentments which the Court affoordeth perfectly pure, and not embroyled with envie, suspitions, and anxieties, those of <hi>Villeroy</hi> after the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Loudun,</hi> would have beene most ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute, having ended a miserable warre, which good, and rationall men, even with commseration detested. All warre ought to bee accounted for the sicknesse and mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and peace for the true constitution, and wholesome temperature of a state. <hi>A Prince
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12763:37"/>commits no lesse an error in letting slip the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a sure, and honourable peace, than by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitating himselfe rashly, and imprudently into an unjust warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But hee having in the treatie of <hi>Loudun,</hi> more considered publique interest, than par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, saw himselfe in such dis-favour, that hee was constrained to suffer his charges to bee disposed of, as they pleased. Hee in this precipice reteined his ordinary constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as <hi>Colossusses,</hi> though thrown into a ditch, lose not their greatnesse.</p>
            <p>Hee consecrated the houres to pietie, which hee had heretofore employed in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and men wondred to see him give care to Sermons at the same time, when our Kings formerly tooke delight to hearken to him. Heretofore hee sought for God at Court, hee now findes him in retirement. One cannot bee at the same time in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Ierujalem,</hi> and hee who is in <hi>That,</hi> must ever have the window of his soule open to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>This.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this memorable time, which put the vessels into the port of a perfect tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, that had too long floated on the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12763:38"/>in an instant Armes were seene to fall out of the Princes hands, and the designes of a third faction to bee stopped. The King presently advertised him of it, bee caused him to come to <hi>Louure,</hi> and as it were, casting himselfe betweene his armes, put upon him the whole care of his affaires and state.</p>
            <p>Hee shewed him the letters hee had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and which were all ready upon this occasion to bee sent to the Governours of <hi>Provinces;</hi> hee approved them. They were the lines of a good pen, and a brave spirit, who preferring sidelity due to his King and Countrey, before any other obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, had two yeares together wisely and couragiously mannaged a great part of this great and dangerous designe.</p>
            <p>Auncient ministers of state were taken off from affaires, or rather affaires were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved of their good direction, and the three principall offices of state were strayned, and dissolved into one man; the first coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell which <hi>Villeroy</hi> gave the King, was, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store them to their charges, and re-establish the former order.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:12763:38"/>
            <p> The King rejoyced at the returne of <hi>Mounsieur</hi> the Chancellour, as he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored his departure, and frequent teares, which fell from the Queenes eyes, when hee tooke leave of her at <hi>Blois,</hi> shewed the violence which her soule had suffered to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to this change. The Lord Keeper of the Seales, who had more freely yeelded them up, than accepted them againe, received them the second time from the Kings hand, who praysed his vertue and justice; not unlike to <hi>Euphrates,</hi> which never alters his course for the opposition of the highest mountaines. The superintendent of <hi>Finan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> continued his charge with the same in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, but with much more power than before. The Controulership generall of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> was given him, whom <hi>Henry the Great</hi> had entrusted with it, and who hath so much sinceritie, loyaltie, and honour in this charge, that wishes cannot adde to the contentment, which the publique, and his conscience gave him.</p>
            <p>HE went to the Assembly of <hi>Roan,</hi> and carried thither good thoughts, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12763:39"/>wholesome counsels for the service of the King, and the good of the state, not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his dislike, to see that after this great <hi>Crisis,</hi> the malady was not wholly taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Hee made this journey upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hee at his returne, might thinke no more but on the greatest, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake the toyles of Court, and noyse of the Citie. Amongst the many Temples which <hi>Rome</hi> raysed to its fabulous Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that, of <hi>Repose</hi> was in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. Writing to his sonne, the governour of <hi>Lyons,</hi> hee wished him to doe his businesse in the morning, as if he were sure to lose it in the evening.</p>
            <p>HIS most sensible contentments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the mariage of the Marquesse <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leroy,</hi> his grand-childe, with the daughter of <hi>Mounsieur Crequies</hi> grand-childe, <hi>the brave Marshall,</hi> the <hi>Demetrius</hi> of his time, who at the age of threescore and eighteene, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted <hi>Lombardy.</hi> Hee recommended no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so much to this young Lord, as the Kings service, thinking this command com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all other.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:12763:39"/>
            <p> Obey the King, is to performe the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall poynt of the Law; <hi>For who giveth not to Caesar, what belongs to Caesar, is alwayes slack in his dutie towards God.</hi> This is a precept, which the Nobility of <hi>France</hi> should night and day study; It is the gold which the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle advised should bee hanged at the eares of the <hi>Lydian</hi> youth.</p>
            <p>The rules which a great man of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome gave lately to his sonne (an officer of the Crowne) for his better direction, are good for all those, who will walke in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie before heaven, and in honour on earth, I account these the most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: <hi>Render your selfe obedient and at hand neare the King at the houres you shall thinke to bee most acceptable to him, conforme your will to his, seeke for what hee affecteth, make it your principall delight to please him, and to gaine his good favour. To thinke to make your selfe more esteemed by great expence, than by vertue, and frugalitie is an abuse: yea verily, a folly.</hi> All the Philosophers of the universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and of experience, cannot furnish you with better precepts, either to make, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a fortune in Court.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:12763:40"/>
            <p> PRESENTLY after the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the assembly, death violently as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sailed <hi>Villeroy,</hi> but it surprized him not: for he long before was prepared for that day, the last of age, and first of Eternity, and had seene all that, to dye before him, which disturbeth the contentment of a sweet death. There are none; but such as are wel prepared to dye, who goe joyfully, and constantly towards death.</p>
            <p>The violence thereof lasted but twice foure and twenty houres, it nothing at all taking away the strength of his judgement, nor vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of his patience, sweetly breathing forth his last in the hope and thirst of eternall life, and in the testimonies of pietie, which hee so religiously had manured all his life time. His body was opened to bee embalmed, and carried to <hi>Magny,</hi> the place of buriall of his ancestors; there was no bloud found in him, he having made his service continue to the last drop.</p>
            <p>The King in words worthy the goodnesse of such a master, and the merit of such a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, shewed he felt in his heart this losse, and the remembrance of what hee dying, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12763:40"/>unto him. The Prince who looseth an auncient servant able to give him coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell without passion, and to tell him truth without flattery, is well assured of the felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his state, if his affaires be not sensible of such a losse.</p>
            <p>INSTANTLY after <hi>Villeroy</hi> had yielded up the Ghost, the Chauncellor, the Keeper of the Seales, Mounsieur Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Ianin,</hi> who knew true amities goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a tombe, sayd to the King, he could not better witnesse he had loved the father, then by affecting, his.</p>
            <p>The King made his love appeare by send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a message to <hi>Mounsiour de Halincourt that as he in Mounsieur Villeroy had lost a good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so he should in him ever find a good Master.</hi> His letters next day after his death on the thirteenth of December, expressed the sorrow of his Maiesty. <hi>It is a losse</hi> (these are his words) <hi>which I particularly ressent, not onely as acknowledging, and having tryed in divers oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, together with his fidelity &amp; affection the effects of the long experience he had acquired in the mannage of my affaires, and how necessary,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12763:41"/>and profit able he was for me.</hi> There is no ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice so great which is not well requited with such wordes, and none can be found to be more excellent, for the honour of his Tombe. As it is an imprudence in al kind of discourses to speake things superfluous, and from the purpose, so it is a treachery to omit the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary. I might account my selfe culpable both of the one and other, if I should forget that the King by the like effects of his affection commanded <hi>Mounsieur</hi> the Duke of <hi>Venta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> and <hi>Mounsieur</hi> the Marshall De <hi>L'Esdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guieres,</hi> to accord the difference betweene <hi>Mounsieur D'Halincourt,</hi> and <hi>Mounsieur De S. Chaumont,</hi> and that this difference was so incensed, that although the wills of men were well united in what conscerned the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Maiesty, and common safery, yet passion disuniteth the affections of many.</p>
            <p>One whom the King drew from his Councell of state to give him the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> and gouernment of this prouince, made an excellent remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance upon this.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:12763:41"/>
               <l>Whose lively reasons, plum'd with words as strong,</l>
               <l>Through generous soules (at arrowes) passe along.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That it may appeare that the Kings Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in such like divisions should not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their affections and iudgements to run after those interests, which appertaine not to them, but reserve them wholly, for the service of his Maiesty, for publique ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities and their particular quiet; for all partialities finally conclude in seditions.</p>
            <p>The name of <hi>Villeroy</hi> hath beene so cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated every where, that the memory there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of shall eternally bee much honoured. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals never are present at Ceremonies of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, but for Princes, yet here five, <hi>Bevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacqua, Vicenzo, Bonzy, Vbaldino,</hi> and <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sino</hi> were present at his obsequies, and funerall Sermon, learnedly and elegantly pronounced by a Iesuit in the Church of St. <hi>Lewis</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> The Archbishop of <hi>Lyons;</hi> who performed it so worthily, &amp; who so well understands the Kings service, tooke upon him the care of this dutie. There, <hi>Italian La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> many <hi>Lords,</hi> infinite other, <hi>French</hi> by birth, or affection were to be seene.</p>
            <p>Behold what I have observed upon the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12763:42"/>life of <hi>Mounsieur Villeroy,</hi> that every one may make an estimate of his merits and services. I was bound unto it, being unable to forget the account hee made of my writings, the good liking he delivered of them to <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> the pains he pleased to take; not to see, and slightly overlooke them (for every one can doe so:) but to correct them, which none could doe so well. I, in this have often found, that it is an incredible contentment to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ones labours to a great and sincere judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For if he like them, others are not to be feared, if he approve them not, one will strive to doe better: I desired the one more than the other. For <hi>approbation is very pleasing, but correction more profitable.</hi> I wish the gratitude of my duty may in this appeare: for <hi>it is a kinde of ingratitude to tell, but to few, the good we have received from any one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King wanteth not worthy men to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this place, and <hi>France</hi> in the production of brave spirits, is the golden branch of <hi>Sybil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> which loosing one loafe, thrusts out an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, but there goeth much time to make up a man of such experience; besides, it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable helpe to have been under the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12763:42"/>of <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> and to have obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that hee proposed, what he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve, and put in execution what hee had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved on.</p>
            <p>THE prosperity wee enjoyed in the first yeares of his reigne, were likewise the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the great prudence and magnanimity of this prince, who had in the calme foreseene from whence the storme might come, and how to divert it. It had perhaps continued longer, had the like order beene still observed, &amp; those who have observed the difference of times and events, have compared the advices of this great King, to the citie of <hi>Athens,</hi> whose clymate was so temperate, that in what part of the world soever one were, he had cause to be sorry, he enjoyed not so sweet, and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some an abode.</p>
            <p>THE losse of a good servant is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily repaired, whole Ages are necessary to make <hi>Villeroyes. Augustus</hi> lost two, which hee never found againe among so many millions of men in his Empire. His legions were as soone made up, as dissolved: The sea saw
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12763:43"/>new fleets, where it had swallowed up the old: Buildings rise from out of their ruines, more pompous and splendid than they were; but all the time of his reigne he was heard to bewayle <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and <hi>Mecenas,</hi> finding not any worthy to supply their places.</p>
            <p>I am deceived; The losse of a good servant is in some sore repayred, when his counsels are followed, and the Maximes are observed, which his long experience authorized, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible principles of verity. It is not todesirea slight happines to the state, to wish that <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieur Villeroy</hi> were alwayes in employment by his good advice, since divine providence permitteth not him to be personally therein, and that it principally consisteth in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of that wholesome counsell which he alwayes gave his masters: <hi>To prevent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and not to neglect light faults, lest they draw on great.</hi> The first examples of justice and the first acts of revenge, are the best, and such as fall upon the authours of sedition, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it. <hi>Phalaris</hi> did onely one act of lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice by shutting him in the brazen Bull, who invented it.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:12763:43"/>
            <p> BVT it is enough: the rest is in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story, I have but this one thing to say. I must after an excellent &amp; free discourse published at <hi>Roan</hi> in the beginning of the assembly, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that <hi>Mounsieur Villeroy</hi> was the <hi>First<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mover</hi> of state affaires, the miracle of <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and <hi>Wisedome,</hi> the Sphere from whence those brave spirits descended, which recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Kings commands; And in a word, the <hi>Archimus</hi> who made all <hi>Europe</hi> move; and who as <hi>Archimedes</hi> breathed out his last, over his figures, and died in great and sublime me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations for the glory of this Crowne, and the reformation of disorders.</p>
            <trailer>The end.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12763:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>